<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<infotexts language="English" nowhitespace="false" translatedname="English">
  <!-- Stahlhelm M42 (Heer) — “Normandy” camo — ckl64 lot 2979 -->
  <entityname.oh_42_wh_c1>Stahlhelm M42 (Heer) — “Normandy” camo — ckl64 lot 2979</entityname.oh_42_wh_c1>
  <entitydescription.oh_42_wh_c1>Issued from the ckl works in mid-1944, this size 64 shell carries the lot number 2979. Its Normandy camouflage was brushed on hastily, earthy greens and browns breaking up the outline beneath the hedgerows. Mud still clings in the rim’s recesses, as if set down in a foxhole after a summer storm. Some say it was left where its wearer fell, the liner stiffened by time, the steel carrying the silence of the bocage where battles raged and ended in whispers.</entitydescription.oh_42_wh_c1>
  <!-- Stahlhelm M42 (Heer) — single decal — ET64 lot 3119 -->
  <entityname.oh_42_wh_sd1>Stahlhelm M42 (Heer) — single decal — ET64 lot 3119</entityname.oh_42_wh_sd1>
  <entitydescription.oh_42_wh_sd1>Stamped ET64 with lot number 3119, this helmet followed the later-war pattern of single-decal issue. The rough-textured paint has dulled to a matte tone, broken only by the army shield applied neatly to the left side. Its chin strap and liner remain intact, the leather drawn tight, pins unmoved since the factory. A piece that speaks less of camouflage and more of regulation — carried as issued, with its insignia still proud against the steel.</entitydescription.oh_42_wh_sd1>
  <!-- M42 Luftschutz — beaded — EF66 lot 1047 -->
  <entityname.oh_42_ls_bd1>M42 Luftschutz — beaded — EF66 lot 1047</entityname.oh_42_ls_bd1>
  <entitydescription.oh_42_ls_bd1>The bead along the skirt gives it away — a strengthened run turned aside from field issue and sent to the Luftschutz. This EF shell, size 66, carries the civil decal over rough paint, its edge rubbed smooth where fingers found the brim in dark stairwells. People remember sirens and cellar doors; the helmet remembers dust, broken glass, and the quick breath before the all-clear. A practical piece, worn hard in the nights when fires walked the rooftops.</entitydescription.oh_42_ls_bd1>
  <!-- M42 Luftschutz — beaded — hkp64 lot 1554 -->
  <entityname.oh_42_ls_bd2>M42 Luftschutz — beaded — hkp64 lot 1554</entityname.oh_42_ls_bd2>
  <entitydescription.oh_42_ls_bd2>The bead rolled into the skirt marks a different duty—steel set aside for the Luftschutz. This hkp shell, size 64, lot 1554, carries a civic badge over rough wartime paint; the strap’s hard sheen and the dry creak of the liner hint at long, anxious nights. It remembers stairwells and blackout curtains, the dust under cellar steps, and the hush between siren notes when a city counted breaths in the dark.</entitydescription.oh_42_ls_bd2>
  <!-- Stahlhelm M42 — ckl64 lot 3698 -->
  <entityname.ww2_stahlhelm_m42_base>Stahlhelm M42 — ckl64 lot 3698</entityname.ww2_stahlhelm_m42_base>
  <entitydescription.ww2_stahlhelm_m42_base>A late-issue M42 from the ckl works, size 64, lot 3698. The paint lies flat and unadorned, a field finish without heraldry. Its rim shows a bright line where it was gripped again and again, the inside still holding the smell of old leather. Honest steel, carried by men in the last years of the war, marked more by wear than by symbols.</entitydescription.ww2_stahlhelm_m42_base>
  <!-- Luftschutz M38 Gladiator — 3-piece -->
  <entityname.oh_38g3>Luftschutz M38 Gladiator — 3-piece</entityname.oh_38g3>
  <entitydescription.oh_38g3>Pressed for the Luftschutz, the Gladiator style favored comfort and coverage in streets gone dark.Three joined sections shape the crown and skirt, paint laid matte so light would not catch on it.It remembers stairwells, torchlight, and the hush after sirens when neighbors counted the seconds together.</entitydescription.oh_38g3>
  <!-- Luftschutz M38 Gladiator — 2-piece -->
  <entityname.oh_38g2>Luftschutz M38 Gladiator — 2-piece</entityname.oh_38g2>
  <entitydescription.oh_38g2>A rarer two-piece shell, the crown and skirt joined cleanly with the Luftschutz badge sharp over the brow.A rear size mark sits neat above smooth paint.It carries the quiet work of its branch—doorways, stairwells, and the dust that settles after the all-clear.</entitydescription.oh_38g2>
  <!-- Luftschutz M38 Gladiator — 1-piece -->
  <entityname.oh_38g1>Luftschutz M38 Gladiator — 1-piece</entityname.oh_38g1>
  <entitydescription.oh_38g1>The scarce one-piece Gladiator shell, pressed in a single form and marked with the Luftschutz eagle at the brow.Light and rigid, it sits close to the head; the rear size stencil is crisp, the paint smooth to the touch.It recalls wardens moving through stairwells and courtyards, guiding voices in the dark.</entitydescription.oh_38g1>
</infotexts>